In this task, we are going to model an online
ticketing system for a theater. For this system,
we are already given a very thorough description
that we basically just need to read out and
translate into a working-class diagram. Later
on, we'll also make an object diagram based on
the class diagram. But let's just start with
the class diagram itself. The test gives us
some additional notes here for the data types
that we might use in our attributes. We can
use some given classes, namely 'Price' for
prices, 'CalendarDate' for calendar dates,
and time for clock times. We don't need to model
these in our diagram. We can just assume they
exist and use them as types for our attributes.
We're told that underlined words in the text
already designate the classes that we need in
our diagram. So, finding the classes is pretty
simple. We just need to read a little closer
to find what attributes and methods we need.
So, I'm just going to move this text out of the
way since screen space is a little limited. And
we can start by reading the first paragraph.
A theater, underlined. So, this is definitely
going to be a class. Consists of different rooms,
which themselves consist of seats. So, we have our
theater class. And it consists of different rooms.
We can't really do anything with that yet because
we don't have other classes. But we're told,
each room, the room is also underlined so this
is going to be a class as well, has a name and
each seat has a number. So, we have room and seat.
And pretty clearly, each room has a name. This
is an attribute. So, we have an attribute name
which is going to be a string. And we have
an attribute number for each seat, which is
probably going to be an Int because you could
make it a float. But seat 20.5 doesn't really
sound that nice. So, let's just take whole
numbers and leave it as an Int. We have
no indications of methods here. So, we're
just going to leave these boxes here blank.
It's always important to
leave the boxes themselves.
Since otherwise, it's not syntactically correct
for a class in a UML class diagram. So, we're
just going to delete the text and not the box
itself, just leaving this little empty line here.
For theater's attributes, there's no indication of
any attributes for theater here in the text. So,
we're just going to leave that box
empty as well and leave it like this.
Now we could either go on with the text
and first identify all the classes or
just start working out the relations
between the classes here right away.
I'm just going to start by reading a little
into this here. Consists kind of implies some
kind of relation to other Class because a theater
consists of different rooms. And especially, it
implies some kind of part-whole association. So,
it's definitely either aggregation or composition.
And to determine which of those it is, we just
need to think about the lifetimes of the object
here. The theater is the whole, and the room is
the part, is the lifetime of the room connected
to the lifetime of the theater? So, if we tear
down the theater, are we going to tear down all
the rooms as well? Logically, yes, probably.
So, we are going to make that a composition,
connecting theater to room. And the composition
arrow we get from the drawio here already
has some multiplicity here, at least one,
and nothing on the other side. This is fine.
We can leave it like this. We could remove
the arrowhead. It's not really wrong in this
case. But if we wanted to, we can remove
it and just make it a simple line here.
Basically, the arrowhead implies direction for
the composition. But that's already given here.
Now going further, we have each room has a
name, and each seat has a number. Of different
rooms which themselves consist of seats. So, the
room and seat have a "consist" relation as well.
We'll just model it the same as with the first
consist here. Make that a composition as well.
So, each room is the whole for any number
of seats. The multiplicity up here,
one is fine. We can leave that. We're just
going to remove the arrowhead for this.
With that, we have all the information that we can
get from the first paragraph in our diagram. And
we can move on to the second one. Which is, events
are conducted in a theater. This doesn't really do
anything for us yet. But an event is either a film
or a concert. There is underlines. Once again,
that tells us that these are classes. So, we have
the class event. And we have the classes
'Film' and 'Concert'. Each event has a name.
So, you have the name attribute in Event.
Additionally, we have, for a
film, the name of the director
and the main actor stored.
For a concert, the name of the conductor and
the name of the orchestra are stored. So, the
conductor and orchestra are also strings.
We have no indications of methods here. So,
once again, we're going to delete these method
placeholders here and leave this empty box.
But we are told an event is either
film or a concert. This "is" implies
some kind of generalization. So, we have a
generalization arrow here if we can find it.
There it is. I don't know why this is a
dashed line. Let me fix that in a moment.
There we go. And get another one for the relation
from Concert to Event as well. We could make this
join, but it doesn't really matter. It could be
joined in the middle here and then just one arrow
to the event. But this works as well. We can get
rid of these extent labels. Drawio adds these
automatically. But the arrow already means that
this is a generalization. So, we don't really need
that additional information. That's just visual
clutter. That's our generalization between these
three classes here. Got the model correctly. And
we only have one more relation in this paragraph,
which is events are conducted in a theater.
Being conducted in a theater, that's not a
part-whole relationship or anything like that.
Because the event isn't part of the theater,
and the theater isn't part of the event. So, this
is most likely just a simple association here.
We're not going to use the arrow that draw
arrow gives us for that because that has
these weird labels that just say, parent and
child. This is not really all that helpful.
Instead, we are going to add a label that gives us
some indication of what this association is for,
namely conducts. So, the theater conducts an
event or events are conducted in a theater.
But this is basically the same. We just need some
kind of reading direction here because otherwise,
we might read it as an event conducted at the
theater, which doesn't really make sense. So, just
to help the reader, we can add one of these little
reading arrows that I've already prepared here.
Draw arrow doesn't have these, as far as I know.
So, I'm going to copy and paste these that I've
made before and just place them on the label here.
And now we can read this as the theater conducts
an event. This is our association placed. And this
is all the information from the second paragraph.
In the third paragraph, it says a
date, which is once again a class.
Has an event that happens on that date and a
room where it happens. So, this is a lot of
relation to the Class that we already have.
Additionally, the calendar date and time,
as well as the price of the seat for that date
are stored. So, we need three attributes here now.
One for the calendar date. So, just the date,
and then we can use one of those predefined
classes that we were told about in the help
text, namely the calendar date.
It's important here that we make use of
these given classes. Because otherwise,
date as an int or float doesn't really make
sense. And if we don't use these, then we need
to define our own. So, this is really helpful that
these are given to us. We have the time as well.
Using the time class that we are given. And we
have the price for the seats. Which we can
just give as 'price'. And for that, we're using
the Price class. And that's our three attributes.
There's, once again, no indication of
any methods here. So, we're going
to delete this method placeholder.
And that's our date class. Now,
we need to move these around a little bit to make
room for the relations that the date has. Namely,
a date has an event that happens on that date.
So, there's a relation between date and event.
For this, we now need to ask ourselves once again,
is there some kind of part-whole relationship?
If you think about it, the date isn't really
part of the event. And the event isn't really
part of the date. You might argue that
the event might be part of the date. So,
this could be an aggregation. But then again, the
event might be happening anyway. It just depends
on when it happens. So, it's probably more likely
to just give this as a simple association here.
So, we are going to use the
regular line here again.
And we are going to add a little
label that says the date of the event.
And add a reading arrow to clarify the
reading direction. So, now it reads
that this association is the date of the event.
Going a little further along, we can also add
multiplicities here. Because the text says, a
date has an event. So, one date probably has one
event. So, we can add a multiplicity of one on the
side of the event because, at any point in time,
there's probably only going to be one event going
on. And on the other side, if we look at one event
as a film or concert, in this case, the film is
probably going to add more times than just one
day at one specific time. So, on the other side
of the multiplicities, we are going to have one
to infinity. So, this can be a relationship of one
event on however many dates, at least one date.
It can't really be zero to however many
here because the text specifically says
a date has an event. So, this implies
that the event has at least one date.
Then we have the relationship of date has an event
and a room where it happens. So, the date and room
are connected as well. Once again, room and date
don't really have a part-whole relationship. So,
this is just a normal association.
This doesn't really look that nice.
We can change our line build itself. And
then add a reading direction, once again.
A label with a reading direction
that says,
for example, a room is booked for a
specific date. So, we can say booked
or booked for. And add a reading direction as
well. So, the room is booked for a specific date.
Or we can go the other way around and say a
date is taking place in a specific room. So,
taking place. Or just in. And then reading arrow
in the other direction. There we go.
So, some kind of date, some
kind of event is happening in that specific room.
Speaking of that specific room, the text says a
room where it happens. So, not multiple rooms. So,
this is implicated the multiplicity of one
here. You can just leave that as the one here.
And on the other side, the text doesn't really
give any implications. And with the reading
direction going like this, it doesn't really make
sense to add any multiplicity to the other side.
And if we now just go over the paragraph quickly,
a date has an event. Which happens on that date.
This is modeled. And a room where it happens is
our other association here. And the last line just
tells us about the attributes for the date class.
And that's all the information in this paragraph.
Now in the last paragraph, we are told a booking
consists of a date and one or more seats. So,
booking is a class, indicated by the underline
here. Consists of date and one or more seats.
These are classes that we already have.
So, we don't need attributes for this.
But we are told about some methods that booking is
going to have. Namely, a booking has an operation
"readPrice." So, this is going to be our first
method in this class diagram, "readPrice,"
which computes the overall price of all
seats. Since we are talking about the
price of multiple seats and we use the price
class for the price of a single seat and date,
we're just going to use the price class
here as the datatype for the return as well.
Furthermore, a booking has an operation
"send," which sends the booking to the
theater and reserves the selected seats.
So, we're going to add another method here,
which is called "send," which just sends the booking
to the theater and reserves the selected seats.
The booking is being sent away here. So, this
is a method operating on the Class itself. So,
it doesn't need any arguments. And it
has no indicated return type since this
is just sent away to the theater. So, we're
just going to leave this empty like this.
Our "readPrice" function with no arguments
at price return and "send" with no arguments
and no return. There is no indication of
any attributes in this case. We're going
to delete the empty attribute placeholder
here and leave a booking class like this.
Now to the relation. A booking consists
of a date and one or more seats. So,
we have a "consist" relationship again, which
we modeled as a composition further at the top.
But in this case, this doesn't really make
sense because booking and date don't really
have a part-whole relationship. It might
consist of a date and one or more seats.
But we can look at this a little more loosely as
booking just having a relationship to the date.
Namely, being a booking for a specific date
with reading direction from booking to date. Move
a little closer. Let's just leave
it like that. That's good enough.
A booking is for one specific day. So,
we have a multiplicity of one up here.
The booking consists of one or more seats. This
is more of a part-whole relationship here because
the booking is the whole where
the seats are reserved for it.
So, we are going to use an aggregation here.
Going from booking to the seat.
And we're told one or more. So,
the multiplicity on the side of the seat
is going to be one to however many.
And we can remove this multiplicity down here that
drawio added.
Because there's no indication that one seat
might not be part of multiple bookings. So,
having no multiplicity down here makes more
sense than having a multiplicity of one.
And if we just move our lines here a little nicer
or just move the class diagram so that these lines
are even. Then we tidied up our class diagram.
And this is basically all the information that
we can get from this text for this class
diagram. So, we can consider this complete.